Mss.Ms.Coll.76
American Philosophical Society
Smith-Houston-Morris-Ogden Family papers, 1659-1985
Mss.Ms.Coll.76
American Philosophical Society
350.0 Linear feet
The Smith-Houston-Morris-Ogden Family Papers document the history of the Houston, Smith, Ogden, Morris and allied families, beginning in the late 17th century, and continuing through to near the end of the 20th. Among the many treasures in this vast collection are the papers of Pennsylvania Railroad executive Henry Howard Houston (1820-1895), his son, Samuel Frederick Houston (1866-1952), and of Pennsylvania attorney and treasury official, William Meredith (1752-1816). Although the collection contains a great deal of interest with respect to land speculation, commerce, and trade emanating from Philadelphia, the bulk of the Smith Family Papers consists of personal and family correspondence and other papers. Among the largest and most interesting bodies of papers are those of L.M.C. Smith and Eleanor Houston Smith, daughter of Samuel F. Smith. These document the family's progressive attitudes regarding and resource conservation, historic preservation, and their social activism.
350 linear feet.
Houston, Henry Howard, 1820-1895
Houston, Samuel Frederick, 1866-1952
Meredith, William, 1752-1816
Smith Family
Smith, Eleanor Houston
Smith, L.M.C.
Box 350
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Gift of the children of Eleanor Houston Smith and Lawrence M.C. Smith, 1992.
Arrangement note
The large collection has material from many families. The families also intermarried and married into other families, so making sense of these connections while keeping individuals and families more or less discrete units was challenging. Series numbers were assigned to either families (Bonnell Family) or individuals (Gouverneur Morris). Early in the cataloging some series numbers were skipped, anticipating later additions or divisions, but not all skipped numbers have been used. Items within series have been divided into types of material. Within these subseries material is arranged either chronologically, by title, or by correspondent. Some series are not arranged or fully arranged and are not accessible. Consult individual series descriptions for their current status.
Early American History Note
The Smith-Houston-Morris-Ogden Collection is the APS's largest collection. It has a vast array of materials from early America. The APS has on file a 303-page survey of the collection that scholars may want to consult before beginning their research. In general, the collection contains information on business, politics, family and social life, Philadelphia history, land expansion, and estates. A good part Morris portion of the collection comes from Governeur Morris and his wife. The bulk of this material begins with his time as an emissary to France during the early republic and continues to his death. There is also a fairly extensive collection of his wife's correspondence, most of which follows Governeur's death. Her letters touch on issues relating to his estate and to other affairs. It includes discussions of slavery in Virginia and contains correspondence from memebers of the extended Jefferson family. The Ogden's were surveyors and land speculators in the late colonial and early national period. This portion of the collection contains discussion of land, business, politics, and family matters. A significant amount of these papers focus on the operations of a grist mill in New York. There are papers from numerous other prominent families, such as the Clemsons, Morgans, and Lewises, who were related through marriage.
Business and Skilled Trades; Business Records and Accounts; Colony and State Specific History; Correspondence.; Diplomatic History; Diplomatic Material; Early National Politics; Family Correspondence; International Affairs; Land and Speculation; Land speculation; Miscellaneous; Pennsylvania History; Philadelphia (Pa.) -- Commerce.; Philadelphia History; Political Correspondence; Surveying and Maps; Trade
- Graphics, A sample of the graphics available in the Smith Family papers. The following photographs of Ludlow Ogden Smith are from Series 80, Box II. Miniature portrait of Elizabeth Clemson is from Series 31 D -- Thomas Green Clemson.
  - Ludlow Ogden Smith, ca. 1920; 1.0 Photograph(s); Photograph of Ludlow O. Smith standing in front of a house.
  - Ludlow Ogden Smith in Navy uniform, ca. 1919; 1.0 Photograph(s); Portrait of Ludlow Ogden Smith in Navy uniform.
  - Ludlow Ogden Smith, 3/4 portrait, ca. 1919; 1.0 Photograph(s); Half length, 3/4 portrait of Smith in Navy uniform, hat in lap.
  - Elizabeth Baker Clemson, miniature portrait, n. d.; 1.0 Item(s); Miniature portrait of Clemson, painted on porcelain.
  - Susan Ogden Roebuck, carte de visite, n. d.; 1.0 Item(s); 3/4 length portrait of Roebuck, standing behind chair.
  - I. S. Ogden, August 1864, Milwaukee, Wisconsin, 1864 August; 1.0 Item(s); Half length, 3/4 portrait of Ogden.
  - View of Druim Moir gardens
  - View of children posed around Druim Moir fountain
- Series 1: Bonnell Family Papers, 1751-1904; 0.25 Linear feet
- Series 2: Boude Family Papers, 1910-1982; 4.0 items
- Series 3: Bringhurst Family Papers, 1910-1982; 2.0 folders
- Series 4: Brown Family Papers, 1906-1951; 0.25 Linear feet
- Series 5: Chambers Family Papers, 1932-1965; 7.0 folders
- Series 6: Clarkson Family Papers, Bulk, 1950-1959; 1802; 1950's; 2.0 folders
- Series 7: Unassigned
- Series 8: Henry Howard Houston Papers, 1850's-1900; 3.5 Linear feet
- Series 9: Sallie Sherrerd Bonnell Houston Papers, 1879-1919; 2.0 Linear feet
- Series 10: Henry Howard Houston and Sallie S. B. Houston Family Papers, 1920-1977; 0.25 Linear feet
- Series 11: Henry Howard Houston Estate Papers (c. 1880's 1985, bulk 1895 1960's; ca. 17 linear feet), Bulk, 1895-1969; 17.0 Linear feet
- Series 12: Henry Howard Houston, Jr. Papers, 1895-1963; 30.0 items
- Series 13: Samuel Frederic Houston Papers, Bulk, 1890-1959; 1873-1980's; 9.25 Linear feet
- Series 14: Edith Atlee Corlies Houston Papers, 1887-1895; 0.25 Linear feet
- Series 15: Charlotte Harding Shepherd Houston Papers, 1884-1948; 3.75 Linear feet
- Series 16: Samuel Frederic and Charlotte H. S. Houston Family Papers, 1900's-1930's; 8.0 Linear feet
- Series 17: Henry Howard Houston, II Papers (c. 5 linear feet; 1910 1981, bulk 1910-1930's), 1904-1981; 5.0 Linear feet
  - A. Correspondence
    - Smith, John (1875-1930)
      Scope and Contents note
      Military memorabilia from John Smith, including tags, papers, medals, dead flowers.
    - Houston, Samuel (xxxx-xxxx), Folder 1, 1900-1902
  - B. Military Records
    - 28th Division
      - Interesting Item
- Series 18: Samuel Frederic and Charlotte H. S. Houston, Papers of Other Children, 1888-1970; 5.0
- Series 19: Houston Family Papers, 1693-1980; 1.0 Linear feet
- Series 20: Kenner Family Papers, 1840's-1980's; 1.0 Linear feet
- Series 21: Mifflin Family Papers, 1870's-1980's; 0.5 Linear feet
- Series 22: Minor Family Papers, 1940-1985; 0.5 Linear feet
- Series 23: Pike-Hooke-Gove Families Papers, 1659-1972; 0.25 Linear feet
- Series 24: Shepherd-Harding Family Papers, 1700s-1982; 0.5 Lithograph
- Series 25: Strickler Papers, 1880's-1982; 0.25 Linear feet
- Series 26: Woodward Family Papers, 1920-1986; 0.25 Linear feet
- Series 27: Unassigned
- Series 28: Unassigned
- Series 29: Unassigned
- Series 30: Unassigned
- Series 31: Clemson Family Papers, 1810-1960; 2.5 Linear feet
- Series 32: Gouverneur Family Papers, 1751-1774; 19.0 items
- Series 33: Hayes Family Papers, 1690's-1970's; 0.25 Linear feet
- Series 34: Henry Clement Lawrence and the Lawrence Family Papers, 1760's-1970's; 3.0 Linear feet
- Series 35: Levis Family Papers, 1708-1980's; 0.5 Linear feet
- Series 36: Lewis Family Papers, 1690's-1800's; 0.5 Linear feet
- Series 37: Ludlow Family Papers, 1813-1979; 0.25 Linear feet
- Series 38: Massey Family Papers, 1721-1970's
- Series 39: Meredith Family Papers, Bulk, 1830-1879; 1798-1960's; 4.0 Linear feet
- Series 40: Anthony Morgan Papers, 1694-1799; 0.25 Linear feet
- Series 41: Gouvermeur Morris Papers, Bulk, 1730-1836; 1730-1960's; 4.5 Linear feet
- Series 42: Ann Cary Randolph Morris Papers, 1814-1837; 0.75 Linear feet
- Series 43: Gouverneur Morris, Jr. Papers, Bulk, 1834-1876; 1820-1903
- Series 44: Lewis Morris Family Papers, Bulk, 1676-1784; 1676-1980; 101.0 folders
- Series 45: Morris and Allied Families Papers, 1665-1981; 19.0 folders
- Series 46: Morrisania and St. Ann's of Morrisania Papers, 1787-1967; 22.0 folders
- Series 47: Abraham Ogden Family Papers, 1791-1848; 18.0 folders
- Series 48: David A., David B., and David B. Ogden, Jr. Papers, Bulk, 1789-1827; 1789-1981; 54.0 folders
- Series 49: Gouverneur Ogden Papers, 1811-1838; 24.0 folders
- Series 50 Isaac Ogden Papers, Bulk, 1800-1867; 1800-1956; 9.5 Linear feet
- Series 51: Sarah O. (Meredith) Ogden Papers, 1823-1876; 1.5 Linear feet
- Series 52: Isaac and Sarah O. (Meredith) Ogden Family Papers, 1828-1865; 45.0 folders
- Series 53: Meredith Ludlow Ogden Papers, 1842-1865; 12.0 folders
- Series 54: William Morris Meredith Ogden Papers, 1862-1922; 4.5 Linear feet
- Series 55: Samuel Ogden Papers, 1788-1908; 11.0 folders
- Series 56: Thomas Ludlow Ogden Papers, 1803-1844; 1.0 Linear feet
- Series 57: Ogden Family Papers, [1806?]-1960's; 2.25 Linear feet
- Series 58: Unassigned
- Series 59: A. Lewis Smith Papers, 1720-1914; 10.0 Linear feet
- Series 60: Rebecca Levis (Wood) Smith, 1850's-1914; 2.0 Linear feet
- Series 61: A. Lewis and Rebecca Levis Smith Family (1856-1913; 1.75 linear feet), 1.75 Linear feet
- Series 62: Benjamin Hayes Smith Papers (1765-1806; 3 linear feet), 3.0 Linear feet
- Series 63: Margaret Dunn (Mrs. Benjamin H.) Smith Papers, Bulk, 1800-1850; 1774-1850; 0.25 Linear feet
- Series 64: Benjamin Hayes Smith II Papers, 1858-1950; 0.75 Linear feet
- Series 65: Clement Lawrence Smith Papers, 1844-1909; 1.0 Linear feet
- Series 66:
- Series 67:, 1830's-1850's; 4.0 Linear feet
- Series 67a:, 1820-1910; 4.0 Linear feet
- Series 68: Mary L. Smith Papers, 2.0 Linear feet